<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Christ's last sermon, or, The everlasting estate and condition of all men in the world to come. Exactly describing the everlasting, blessed, and happy condition of the children of God in glory for ever: with the everlasting, endlesse, and caseless [sic] condition of wicked men in the world to come forever. Set forth for the comfort of the godly, and for the terror of the ungodly. / By a godly, able and faithfull servant of Jesus Christ, J.H.</title>
            <author>Hart, John, D.D.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1664</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 68 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B03760</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H940B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R177841</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">53299110</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 53299110</idno>
            <idno type="VID">179869</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B03760)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 179869)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2807:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Christ's last sermon, or, The everlasting estate and condition of all men in the world to come. Exactly describing the everlasting, blessed, and happy condition of the children of God in glory for ever: with the everlasting, endlesse, and caseless [sic] condition of wicked men in the world to come forever. Set forth for the comfort of the godly, and for the terror of the ungodly. / By a godly, able and faithfull servant of Jesus Christ, J.H.</title>
                  <author>Hart, John, D.D.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>47 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Andrevv Anderson,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Edinburgh, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno Dom. 1664.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imperfect: stained, tightly bound, print show-through with loss of text.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: National Library of Scotland.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Jesus Christ --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Future life --  Christianity --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:179869:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Chriſts laſt SERMON, OR, The everlaſting eſtate and condition of all men in the World to come.</p>
            <p>Exactly deſcribing the Everlaſting, Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and Happy condition of the Children of God in Glory for ever: With the everlaſting, endleſſe, and eaſeleſſe condition of Wicked Men in the World to come for ever. Set forth for the Comfort of the Godly, and for the Terror of the Ungodly,</p>
            <p>By a godly, able, and faithfull Servant of Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>J. H.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Col. 3 4.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>When Chriſt who is our life ſhall appear, then ſhall ye alſo upon with him in glory.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Mat. 25.34.41.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Come ye bleſſed of my Father, inherit the Kingdome prepared for you from the foundation of the world. Depart from me ye Curſed into everlaſting fire, prepared for the Devil and his Angels.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>EDINB<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RGH,</hi> Printed by ANDREVV ANDERSON, <hi>Anno DOM,</hi> 1664.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:179869:2"/>
            <head>Courteous Reader.</head>
            <p>THere are lately publiſhed ſome uſeful and profitable Sermons, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>Chriſts firſt Sermon.</item>
               <item>A Key to open Heaven-gate.</item>
               <item>The true Chriſtians Path-way to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</item>
               <item>The Plain mans Path-way to Heaven.</item>
               <item>Heavens Glory and Hells Horrour.</item>
               <item>The dreadfull Character of a Drunkara.</item>
               <item>There are alſo ſeverall other ſmall Books needfull to be bought and read, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Beſſie Clarkſon</hi> of <hi>Lanerk.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Lady <hi>Culroſſe</hi> Dream.</item>
               <item>The last Good-night.</item>
               <item>The Hiſtory of <hi>Doctor Fauſtus.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Hiſtory of <hi>Fortunatus.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Hiſtory of <hi>Roſwall</hi> and <hi>Lillian.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Hiſtory of <hi>Guy</hi> Earle of <hi>Warwick.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>No Jeſt like a true Jeſt: <hi>or,</hi> The Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory of Captain <hi>Hynd.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>All which, with variety of other Stories are to be ſold by <hi>Andrew Anderſon.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:179869:2"/>
            <head>CHRISTS LAST SERMON: OR, The everlaſting eſtate and condition of all men in the world to come.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>John 14.2, 3.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>In My Fathers Houſe there are many Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, if it were not ſo, I would have told you: I go to prepare a place for you. And if I go I will come again, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive you unto my ſelf, that where I am there ye may be alſo.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>UR bleſſed Lord and Saviour having in the foregoing Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter acquainted his Diſciples with His departure from them out of this world, He comes here in this, and the three fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Chapters, to give them his laſt fare-well-Sermon, and therein He endeavours principally to comfort the ſad hearts of His Diſciples, who
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:179869:3"/>were now diſconſolate, and caſt down in the ſpirits, under the ſenſe of ſo great and ſad a loſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> as the loſſe of their great and only Lord an Maſter, Jeſus Chriſt: For whom they had le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> and loſt all: Chriſt having acquainted them wit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> His going out of the world, they thereupon pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently begin to be dejected and caſt down at thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ſad news. Lord, ſaid they, have we left all, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> followed Thee, and wilt thou now leave us? ſhall we now be expoſed to the difficultie and dangerous of the wide world? No, ſaith our Saviour, bi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> not diſcouraged, let not your hearts be troubled it is for your good that I go away: <hi>In my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, Houſe are many Manſions, I go to prepar a place for you: And if I go, I will come again and receive you.</hi> You ſhall be no loſers by My going away from you, I will ſurelie make you a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> mends for all your loſſe: There are Manſions of joy in Heaven, that will abundantlie counter vail all your wordlie loſſes. If I go away, it is for your good, for I go to prepare a place for you: And though you have not my bodilie preſence, yet you ſhall have my ſpirituall preſence: <hi>I will ſend you another Comforter that ſhall abide with you for ever. I will not leave you com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortleſſe, I will come unto you:</hi> That is, by My Spirit, to guide you and direct you into all truth, and to bear up your hearts under all thoſe troubles and temptations, which ye ſhall meet withall in the world.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:179869:3"/>
            <p> Having thus briefly given you the ſcope of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he whole, I come now to the words themſelves, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>com whence I raiſe theſe four Propoſitions? firſt, that there are manſions of glory in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven for the people of God hereafter: <hi>In my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Houſe are many manſions.</hi> 2. I note from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ence, that Chriſts aſcenſion was to prepare a place for Believers; <hi>I go to prepare a place for you.</hi> 3. That Chriſt will certainly come again <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>nd receive Believers to Himſelf: <hi>I will come <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gain and receive you.</hi> 4. and laſtly, which ſhall briefly inſiſt upon, I note from hence, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat thoſe manſions of glory prepared by Chriſt or Believers in Heaven, will abundantly recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enſe and make good all the loſſes and all the croſſes which Believers may meet withall in the world.</p>
            <p>I ſhall begin with the firſt of theſe, that there <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re manſions of Glory for Believers hereafter. The point is ſo plain from the words themſelves, that I ſhall onely give you a place or two of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture; in the 84. <hi>Pſalm,</hi> verſ. 11. <hi>The Lord will give grace and glory, and no good thing will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e withhold from them that walk uprightly. Eye <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ath not ſeen, ear hath not heard, neither hath is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ntred into the heart of man to conceive the things which God hath provided for them that love him.</hi> Cor. 2.9. <hi>Come ye bleſſed</hi> (ſaith your Saviour) <hi>inherit the kingdom prepared for you, Mat.</hi> 25.34.
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:179869:4"/>Severall other Scriptures I might give you, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> I ſhall proceed to the uſes of this uſefull poin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Is it ſo then, that there are Manſions of Glor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> for the godly hereafter? then I note from henc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the unſpeakable miſerie of all wicked men bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> here and hereafter: Is there glory in heaven f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Believers? What is there then in hell for Unb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers? if glorie be the portion of the godly, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> will the lot and portion of wicked men b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>The wicked</hi> (ſaith <hi>Pſal.</hi> 9.17.) <hi>ſhall be turm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> into hell, and all the Nations that forget Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> Wicked men ſhall have no part nor portion thoſe glorious Manſions, they are prepated onl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> for the godlie: Wicked men may indeed (whic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſhall but further agravate their ſorrow) behold t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Saints received by Chriſt into glorie, as <hi>Dives</hi> b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> held <hi>La Zarus</hi> in <hi>Abrahams</hi> boſome, but it w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> afar off. Wicked men may at the laſt day he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> that bleſſed ſentence fo <hi>Come ye bleſſed,</hi> but the again alſo they ſhal hear, I and that with a venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance too, that wofull ſentence of, <hi>Go ye curſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> into everlaſting fire, prepared for the Devil an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> his Angels.</hi> It is impoſſible for wicked men, I me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſuch as live and die in ſin unrepented of, to ent<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> into heaven. <hi>Know ye not</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> 6.9.) <hi>that the unrighteous ſhall not inherit <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Kingdom of God.</hi> The Evangeliſt St. <hi>John, Re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> 20.21. ſpeaking of the world to come, which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> foreſaw in his heavenlie viſion, <hi>I ſaw</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:179869:4"/>dead, ſmall and great ſtand before God, and the Books were opened, and another Book was open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, which is the Book of Life: And the dead were judged out of thoſe things which were written in thoſe Books, according to their works.</hi> All the wayes of men, both good and bad, are exactlie written down both in the Book of Gods ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Rememberance, and in the Book of mans own particular Conſcience? <hi>And the ſea gave up the dead which were in it; And Death and Hell</hi> (that is the grave) <hi>delivered up the dead which were in them; And they were judged every man according to their works. And whoſoever was not found written in the Lambs book of life, was caſt into the lake of fire:</hi> There's the event of this judgement to the wicked. But what ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe the Righteous ſhall there have he ſets down in Chap 21. Verſe 3. <hi>Behold</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>the Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle of God is with men, and he will dwell with them and they ſhall be his people, and God himſelf ſhall be with them, and be their God: And God ſhall wipe all tears from their eyes. And there ſhall be no more death neither ſorrow, nor curſing: neither ſhall there be any more pain. He that overcometh ſhall inherit all thing<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> and I will be his God, and he ſhall be <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>on.</hi> A bleſſed priviledge indeed, but what remains for the wicked? See what follows in the eight Verſe. <hi>The fearfull and unbelieving, the abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:179869:5"/>and murtherers, whoremongers, ſorce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, and idolaters, and all lyars ſhall have their part in the lake which burns with fire and brim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone.</hi> A moſt dreadfull Scripture; the Lord awaken every ſecure ſinner, and give them hearts to conſider theſe things before it be too late: For as the Prophet <hi>Malachy</hi> faith, <hi>Mal.</hi> 4.1. <hi>The day cometh that ſhall burn as an Oven, and all the proud, yea, and all that do wickedly ſhall be ſtubble: and the day cometh that ſhall burn them up</hi> (ſaith the Lord Hoſts) <hi>that it ſhall leave them neither root nor branch. Then ſhall they call upon the mountains to cover them, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pon the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>lls to fall upon them, to hide them from the fierceneſs of the wrath of God. O conſider this all you that forget God, leſt he tear you in pieces, and there be none to deliver you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, if there be ſuch manſions of Glory for Believers hereafter, I note from hence the deſperate folly and madneſſe of all thoſe who neglect or deſpiſe their own ſalvation. <hi>Ye will not come to me</hi> (ſaith our Saviour, <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.40.) <hi>that ye might have life. This is the condemnation; that light is come into the world, and men love darkneſſe rather then light, becauſe their deeds are evil.</hi> Chriſt and ſalvation is freely offered to all in the Goſpel: Chriſt invites all to come; <hi>Ho, every one that thirſteth, come to the waters,</hi> Iſa. 55.1. Rev. 22.17. <hi>The Spirit, and the Bride
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:179869:5"/>ſay, Come: and let him that is athirſt, come: and whoſoever will, let him take of the water of life freely.</hi> And as Chriſt invites all to come, ſo he receives all that doth come: <hi>He that comes to me, I will in no wayes caſt him out</hi> (ſaith our Saviour, <hi>Joh.</hi> 6.37. What think you ſinners of theſe Scriptures? will ye come to Chriſt and accept of life and ſalvation, or will ye wilfully caſt away your own ſouls for ever? You ſee here Chriſt offers himſelf to you freely, if you will but receive him. <hi>Come unto me</hi> ſaith our Saviour, <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.28.) <hi>all ye that labour, and are heavy laden, and I will refreſh you.</hi> What <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> will ye come <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> and be ſaved <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> you be ſo de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>peratly mad as to deſtroy your own moſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious and immortall ſouls? When I behold the lives of moſt men, my very heart trembles to think what will, everlaſtingly, become of their precious ſouls; all the care they take is for their bodies, how does money come in, and how they ſhall get riches; but they never conſider how it goes with their ſouls: Ah ſinners, are your bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies everlaſting? Is this world everlaſting? Can any thing but heaven make you happy? Are not your ſouls everlaſting? will ye rather caſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way your ſouls, then leave your luſts, for ſin and you muſt part, orelſe heaven and your ſouls will never meet? He that doth not leave his ſins on
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:179869:6"/>this ſide the grave by Repentance, ſhall find <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſins to meet him on the other ſide the gravel <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> condemn him. If you live in your ſins, ye ſha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> die in your ſins: Yea, die everlaſtinglie for you ſins. Sinners, I beſeech you conſider, are yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> fit to die, are you fit to live in another world are you prepared for heaven? If not, let me te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> you, you are fit for nothing but hell, and hell<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> prepared for you. Sinners, what do you do What do you mean to do are you yet a ſleep? Al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Lord, what a harveſt will hell have in theſe ſin full daies? What preparations do men make ſo heaven? Are not they that were filthie. filthi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll? What men were, that they are ſtill: Thoug<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> God is every day tumbling men into their graves yet no man mends his pace for heaven. Sinners you hear all this, but can you bear all this? Le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> me give you two or three properties of a man fit<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted for hell, and I beſeech you try and examin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> your own ſouls by them.</p>
            <p>The firſt propertie of a man fitted for hell, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Obduration: A ſtone you know is fitted to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend, it is its propertie to fall, downwards: Hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe makes fitneſſe. The way to Hell is from burning to burning, from a ſeared Conſcience to a damned ſoul.</p>
            <p>A ſecond propertie of a man fitted for wrath is alienation; eſtrangedneſſe to God ſpeaks fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to wrath, and it is a ſign that the Soul is
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:179869:6"/>fitted for utter darkneſſe. There are but two ſteps to death, firſt, the ſinner ſaith he will have no fellowſhip with God: And ſecondlie, God ſaith, he ſhall have no fellowſhip with him: Now is the ſinner judged, now fit for hell, then judge ye, the Execution onlie is wanting: And the Devil is not uſuallie backward to perform his of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice: The ſinner is upon the Gallows as it were, he wants but turning off, unleſſe Chriſt ſteps in with a reprieve, that ſoul is utterlie loſt.</p>
            <p>A third propertie of a man fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ted for Hell, is Prophaneneſſe: Prophaneneſſe is the badge of a wicked perſon: Wickedneſſe in the life ſpeaks out a curſed ſoul. You may know what Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie men are of by their Language: <hi>By their Fruits ye ſhall know them.</hi> When mens words and works are the Language of Hell, what need any further inquirie what Countrie men, or to what place they belong: You may read Hell in their very faces. <hi>The tree is known by his fruit,</hi> ſaith our Saviour, <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.20. Mens lives fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhew what their ends are like to be: As the Tree falls, ſo it lyes: As ſinners live, ſo they uſuallie die: Every mans life lively beſpeaks what they are, and what they ſhall be hereafter: If men will go on in the broad way of ſin, you know where their journies end will be: <hi>Broad is the way that leadeth to deſtruction, Mat.</hi> 7.13. I know not what lives you live, but to be ſure you
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:179869:7"/>may either ſpell Heaven or Hell in them. If ye would know the frame of your ſouls, then view your lives; your ſouls breath out themſelves either into the boſom of God or the Devils and into whoſe boſom you breath out your ſouls here in this life, into that boſom you will cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eath them out in death. Fitting grace for heaven you ſee is no trifle, your eternall e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate depends upon it. Sinners, why do you put off this work as a triſle, and why do you put it off till death? I dare ſay, that man would ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be holy if be could help it, that will not be holy till he die; he would never have to do with Chriſt if he could avoid, that will not be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with him before he is ready to leave this world: when death is fitting the ſoul for hell, then, and never till then to be looking af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter heaven. Ah, Lord, that ever thoſe men ſhould have precious and immortall Souls to damn themſelves: they that look no after hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven till they come to their death-beds, are uſual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly croſt in their folly; they are then either ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prized with infirmities of body, and ſo diſinabled to perform ſo great a work; or elſe ſurprized in their ſouls, and ſo unfitted and indiſpoſed to it: either they have no ſtrength or no heart to it, and ſo dye in their ſins, and periſh eternally. Wicked men would never leave ſinning, if they did not ceaſe living, and that is one reaſont to ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:179869:7"/>the infinitneſſe or everlaſtingneſſe of the puniſhment of wicked men in hell. The dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in hell are under eaſeleſſe and endleſſe ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings, becauſe they would have ſinned alwayes, if they had lived alwayes: wicked men would have no end of their lives here, they would live ever, that they might ſin ever; therefore the Lord giveth them a life, not ſuch a one as they would have, but ſuch a one as they deſerve to have, which is indeed a death for ever: wicked men ſhall die eternally for ſin, becauſe they would have lived eternally in ſin.</p>
            <p>In the third place, I beſeech you note from hence, what a bleſſed thing it is to be a Child of God: Is it ſo, that there are manſions of Glory for Believers in Heaven hereafter, then Believers are the onely happy Men and Women in the World. Were it not for the hopes of Heaven, the condition of Gods Children might be ſad enough. <hi>if in this life onely we had hope, we were of all men moſt miſerable,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.19. But the hopes of Gods Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren are in the life to come; therefore they are of all men moſt bleſſed. The happineſſe of a Child of God is not in what he enjoyes here below, but in what he ſhall enjoy hereafter in Glory. The beſt things of a Child of God are unſeen things: <hi>Whilſt we look not</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>at the things which are ſeens, but a the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:179869:8"/>things Which are not ſeen: For the things which are ſeen are temporal but the things that are no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ſeen are eternall,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.18. And in 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 3, 4. <hi>Bleſſed be the God and Father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, which according to His abundance mercy hath begotten us again unto a lived hope by the reſurrection of Jeſus Chriſt from the dea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> To an Inheritance incorruptible, and undefiled that fadeth not away; reſerved in heaven for you who are kept by the power of God, through Faith unto Salvation.</hi> The Apoſtle here excellent<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ſets forth the condition of a Child of God, and that in ſeverall Regards. Firſt, They are b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> gotten again, by Chriſt, to an Inheritance poſſiblie they may loſe all here below for H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ſake: But yet here is the comfort of a Child <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> God, he is Heir to a great Eſtate in the ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> World: There is an Inheritance for him, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that is a ſure one: In ſix Regards: Firſt, I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> not a corruptible, but an incorruptible one. S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> condly, it's an undefiled one: And thirdlie, it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> a laſting, yea, an everlaſting one, it fadeth no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> away. Fourthly, it's reſerved for them ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> they come to age. Gods Children, in this life are not at full age, therefore they are nor cap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of enjoying ſo great a happineſſs, which God will hereafter beſtow upon them. Fifthlie, it reſerved for them in a ſafe place. Many mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> leave great eſtates here for their children, whi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:179869:8"/>they are often cheated of; But the Inheritance of Gods Children is reſerved by God for them in Heaven where neither Moth doth corrupt, nor Theiſ ſteals away. And laſtlie, as the Inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance is reſerved for the Children of God, ſo the People of God are preſerved for their Inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance: Henven if reſerved for them, and they are preſerved for Heaven: They are kept by the mightie power of God through faith un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Salvation.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, are there ſuch Manſion of glorie for Believers hereafter, then I beſeech you try and examine your own ſouls, whether or no ye be in the faith: And let me exhort you in the Name of Chriſt, ſeriouſlie to ſet about the work of Salvation. You ſee what great and glorious things there are laid in ſtore for Gods Children hereafter: Then I beſeech you, labour to get an intereſt in Chriſt here, that so you may partake of thoſe glorious Manſions hereafter. How greatlie ſhould the conſideration of theſe things draw out our hearts, in longings and pan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings after God? <hi>When ſhall I come and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear before God?</hi> ſaith <hi>David, Pſalm 42.1. As the Hart panteth after the Water-brooks, ſo panteth my ſoul after thee, O God: My ſoul thirſteth for God for the living God. When ſhall I come and appear before God?</hi> And if <hi>David</hi> and ſuch longings after the enjoyment of God
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:179869:9"/>in his Ordinances here, what deſires th<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ought we to have after the full enjoyment God himſelf in glory hereafter. Are there <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> manſions of glory to be had hereafter, <hi>W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> manner of perſons ought we to be then in all ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of godlineſſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And then laſtly, If there be ſuch Manſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of glory, then let me exhort you all, even now this your day, to ſet your hearts at work ſeeking after thoſe great things of Eterni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>. Let every Soul of you thus reaſon with you ſelves, Are there ſuch glorious things hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and am I the man or woman that ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy them? I remember a ſtory of <hi>Gauls,</hi> w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> having once taſted the ſweet Wine of <hi>Ita<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> preſently enquired after the Countrie, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver reſted till they had gotten it. I have he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> given you, as it were, a fore-taſte of that H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Wine which Believers ſhall drink here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after in Glory; now if you find any ſweetne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> in it, let not your hearts be at reſt till you com<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> to the Countrie it ſelf, where are Rivers thoſe ſweet Pleaſures, and that for evermore. Martyr ſuffering death, one asked him the cau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> why he ſuffered? Saith he in the words of t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> Apoſtle, <hi>Eye hath not ſeen, ear hath nor heart neither hath it entred into the heart of man<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> conceive the things which God hath prepared f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> them that love him.</hi> The naming of wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:179869:9"/>wrought ſo effectually on the mans heart, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e immediately became a Chriſtian, and after <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ffered death of His Names ſake. You have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ad not onely one, but very many Scriptures <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pened to you, I beſeech you let not all be in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ain. We read in <hi>Mark</hi> 10.17. how the young <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>an came running to Chriſt, ſaying, <hi>Good Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter , what ſhall I do to inherit eternall life?</hi> O that you, ever you that hear me this day, would <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ow alſo come running unto Chriſt, ſaying, What ſhall we do to partake of theſe glorious <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hings here revealed? Methinks, thoſe things <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hould greatly incourage you all, old and young <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ich and poor, now to get an intereſt in Chriſt. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ou that are poor, and have but little in this world, conſider there are as great things in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he world to come for you, as for others. The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ooreſt Beggar ſhall have as great a portion in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he world to come, as the greateſt Prince. No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in this world can ſatisfie a chils of God: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll the glory of the world its but the portion of Reprobate: and will a Reprobates portion <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erve you? will a Dogs portion ſatisfie you? <hi>I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ccount all things in the world</hi> (ſaith the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>le) <hi>but as dung. Phil.</hi> 3.4. There are other <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hings to be ſought after; See what our Saviour <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aith, <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.33. <hi>Seek ye firſt the king dome of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eaven and the righteouſneſſe thereof:</hi> let that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> your firſt indeavour. <hi>Strive to enter in at the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:179869:10"/>ſtrait gate,</hi> though the paſſage benever ſo ſtra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> yet if it be the way to glory, ſtrive to enter <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> thereat. Conſider, God hath given you N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, capable of ſuch glorious things as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> are, God might have made you bruit Bea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> and then there had been an end of you: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> God hath made you creatures capable of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> higheſt excellency, and therefore being of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> a Nature, it highly concerns you to ſeek af<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ſuch things as may give ſatisfaction to you<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſouls. Men live as if they were capable of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> things elſe but meat, and drink, and cloaths; if there were no higher things which conce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> our ſouls hereafter. The heathens could <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> lieve that man was created for greater thing then theſe here below: and if we who have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> great and glorious things revealed to us in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Goſpel, ſhall we neglect the looking after then how juſt ſhall our condemnation be? <hi>For <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſhall we eſcape, if we neglect ſo great ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? Heb.</hi> 2.3.</p>
            <p>I come now to the ſecond Point, and that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> this; That Chriſts Aſcenſion was to prepar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> place for Believers: <hi>I go to prepare a place <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> you.</hi> As Chriſt came down from heaven to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> for ſinner, ſo Chriſt aſcended up to Heaven that believing ſinners might live with him hen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> after. Had not Chriſt aſcended into Heaven He had not finiſht the work of our redemption
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:179869:10"/>and indeed the great ſupport of a Child of God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> yes in his conſideration. <hi>It's Chriſt that died, yea, rather that is riſen again, and now ſits at the right hand of God, making interceſſion for us, Rom.</hi> 8.34. <hi>Father, I will</hi> (ſaith Chriſt, <hi>John</hi> 17.24.) <hi>that thoſe whom thou haſt given <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>me, may be with me where I am. If Chriſt be not riſen</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>then is our preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vain, and our Faith is vain, and we are yet in our ſins.</hi> But, as ſureas Chriſt died. ſo the Apoſtle proves. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. that he roſe again, and aſcended up into heaven. That's an excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Scripture, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.25. <hi>He was delivered for our offences, and raiſed again for our juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation.</hi> Our bleſſed Saviour firſt appearing to <hi>Mary Magdalen</hi> after his Reſurrection, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently ſends her to his Diſciples with the joyfull news of his Aſcenſion, <hi>John</hi> 20.17. <hi>Go to my Brethren, and ſay unto them, I aſcend to my Father, and your Father; to my God, and your God.</hi> O how joyfull is the conſideration of Chriſts Aſcenſion to a Child of God? Now may a Child of God ſay, he hath a friend in the Court; and a friend in the Court, we uſe to ſay, is betcer then a penny in the purſe. Every Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liever hath Chriſt for his friend in the Court of Heaven, and that's more worth to them then thouſands of gold and ſilver. Chriſt is in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven pleading the cauſe for Believers: <hi>If any
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:179869:11"/>man ſin</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 2.2.) <hi>we have an advocate with the Father, Jeſus Chriſt righteous.</hi> And it is good for Believers <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Jeſus Chriſt is in heaven pleading their cauſe w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> God: ſo it is good for them that he is there <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſenting and perfuming all their Prayers to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the Father. Whatſoever it is that we want that may do us good, Chriſt is ready to beg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> us of His Father. Father (ſaith Chriſt) theſe may friends, and for them I have ſhed my blo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> therefore, O Father, <hi>I will that they may with me, to behold my glory.</hi> That is an excel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Scripture, <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.25. <hi>Wherefore he is able <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> to ſave to the uttermoſt thoſe that come unto <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> by him: ſeing he ever liveth to make interceſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> for them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Is it ſo then, that Chriſt Aſcenſion was prepare a place for Believers, then this ſhort encourage Believers to be willing to do or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> any thing here for Chriſt: What was that made the Saint ſuffer ſo joyfully <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Chriſt? was it not this, the aſſurance of God love in Chriſt to them? What was it that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> up <hi>Iobs</hi> ſpirit ſo patiently under all his ſuff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings? <hi>I know</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>though worms deſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> my body, yet my Redeemer liveth, and I ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> ſee Him with theſe eyes. We know</hi> (ſaith the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.1.) <hi>if our earthly houſe of this
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:179869:11"/>berna<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er nalce were diſſolved, we have a building of Jod, an houſe not made with hands, etrnall in the heavens.</hi> The aſſurance of heaven will make as willing to do or ſuffer any thing for Chriſt. There is that in heaven that will abundantly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ompence and make good all our loſſes on earth. O Chriſtians, I beſeech you conſider, you can <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> either do too much or ſuffer too much for the getting of heaven. The Apoſtles were as great ſufferers for the Kingdom of Heaven as ever any were, and yet what account did they make of it? <hi>We reckon</hi> (ſay they) <hi>that the ſuffering of this preſent world, are not worthy to be compared with the glory that ſhall be revealed in us,</hi> Rom. 8.18. <hi>If we ſuffer with Chriſt, we ſhall alſo reign with Chriſt,</hi> 2 Tim. 2.12.</p>
            <p>A third point I noted was this, That Chriſt wil come again, and receive Believers to Himſelf: The point is clear from the words themſelves, <hi>I will come again and receive you.</hi> But a little to illuſtrate the Point, I ſhall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to ſhew you by Scripture that it is ſo: And ſecondly, how it is ſo. Firſt, that it is ſo, that Chriſt will come again, ſee that poſitive Scripture in <hi>Acts</hi> 1.10. <hi>And while they looked ſtedfaſtly into heaven, behold two men ſtood by them in white apparel, which alſo ſaid, Ye men of Galileo, why ſtand ye here gazing up into heaven? his ſame Ieſus which is taken up from you into
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:179869:12"/>heaven, ſhall ſo come in like manner as ye ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ſeen him go into heaven.</hi> Here is the point y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ſee confirmed by Scripture, and that by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> mouths of Angles: As ſure as Chriſt is gone heaven, and as ſure as he now fitteth at Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> right hand in Heaven; ſo ſure will he come gain at the laſt day, and receive Believers <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Himſelf. And then how Chriſt will come: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>ſhall come in power and great glory, Matth. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> 30. And ſecondly, He will come ſudden<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>even as a thief in the night.</hi> Firſt, he ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> come in power; irreſiſtible power againſt ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners. I beſeech you ſinners conſider, you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> not be able to ſtand when He appears, for as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> is all powerfull in himſelf, ſo will He come at<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with an innumerable company of glori<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Saints and Angels. <hi>Behold</hi> (ſaith <hi>Jude</hi>) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Lord commeth with ten thouſand of His Sai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> to execute judgement upon all, and to convi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> all.</hi> 1 Theſ. 1.7, 8, 9. <hi>The Lord Jeſus ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> revealed from heaven with his mighty Angles <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> flamming fire, taking vengeance on them th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> know not God, and obey not the Goſpel of our Lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Jeſus Chriſt, who ſhall be puniſhed with everla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing deſtruction from the preſence of the Lord, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> from the glory of His power.</hi> Though God b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> long ſuffering towards ſinners, yet will he no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> always ſuffer ſinners to go unpuniſhed. <hi>The So<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> of man ſhall come in His glory, &amp; all the holy An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:179869:12"/>with him, Mat.</hi> 25.31. And ſecond lie, he ſhal <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ome ſuddenlie and ſwiftlie: Swiftlie, <hi>even as the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ightning.</hi> And ſuddenlie, <hi>as a thief in the night, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Pet.</hi> 3. Thoſe ſcoffers there mocked and ſcof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ed at the doctrine of Chriſts comming to judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; But ſaith the Apoſtle in the ninth verſe, <hi>Though the Lord be long ſuffering, yet he is not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ack concerning his promiſe: But the day of the Lord will come as a thief in the night.</hi> Though ſinners may think Chriſt long, yet they ſhall find him ſure. The comming of Chriſt will be ſudden to ſinners in two reſpects: Sudden in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of their expectation; He will come before they look for Him; and ſudden, in regard of their unpreparedneſſe: Chriſt will come to ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners before they are ready for Him, they will be then to ſeek for Oyl in their Lamps. Chriſt (as one ſaith) though he hath leaden feet, yet he hath iron hands: though God be long ere he does ſtrike, yet when He doth ſtrike, He will be ſure <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>o ſtrike home. <hi>Yet a little while and He that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſh all come will come, and will not tarry.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now the uſe which I ſhall make of this point ſhall be onely this: Will Chriſt come a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain and receive Believers? then let me exhore you all to believe in the Lord Jeſus Chriſt: Would you be received by Chriſt into glory, then I beſeech you labour to receive Chriſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nto your ſouls by believing. If Chriſt do not
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:179869:13"/>live in you by faith here, you ſhall never <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> with Chriſt in glory hereafter. It is unbe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> that is the ſoul-damning ſin: <hi>He that believe not is condemned already, Iohn</hi> 3.18. <hi>He that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieveth ſhall he ſaved, but he that believeth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſhall be damned, Mark.</hi> 16.16. <hi>He that believ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> on the Son hath everlaſting life; But he t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> believeth not the Son, ſhall not ſee life, but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> wrath of God abideth on him, John</hi> 3. 36.</p>
            <p>Another Uſe which I muſt make of this poi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> might be this, To comfort and encourage <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> people of God in all their ſufferings and loſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Art thou in poverty? Doth the world frown <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> thee? Are thy afflictions and loſſes many a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> great? Let not your hearts be troubled: Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> is gone to prepare a place for you, and Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> will come again and receive you; Therefore <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> not diſcouraged. What though you meet w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> many rubs and ſtops in your way? Yet you m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> be ſure to get to glory at the laſt. <hi>Conſider th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> through many tribulations we muſt enter i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> the Kingdom of Heaven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The fourth and laſt Obſervation which I o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ſerved, was this, That thoſe Manſions of Glo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> prepared by Chriſt for Believers in Heaven, w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> abundantly recompenſe and make good all th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Loſſes and all the Croſſes which Believers m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> here meet withall in the world. <hi>Let not yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> hearts be troubled, in my Fathers houſe are m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:179869:13"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>y manſions. Sell all</hi> (ſaith our Saviour) <hi>and follow me, &amp; thou ſhalt have treaſure in heaven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For further proſecution of this uſefull Point, I ſhall proceed to handle it firſt doctrinallie, and then Applicatorilie; And for the Doctrinal part, I ſhall endeavour to ſhew you firſt, what thoſe Manſions of glorie are which are laid up for Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers: And ſecondlie, what thoſe loſſes are which Believers may here meet withall: And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>hen laſtly, how thoſe Manſions of glorie do make good the loſſes and croſſes which Believers meet with in the world: And to begin with the firſt, what thoſe Manſions of glorie are which are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aid up for Believers in heaven: And all that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>an be ſaid of this, will be but as it were the light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of a Candle to the Sun: For it comes infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>telie ſhort of the skill either of men or Angels <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>o expreſſe, as the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Eyes hath not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>een, ear hath not heard, neither hath it entred in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> the heart of man to conceive the things which God hath prepared for them that love him,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 9. The glorie of the glorified Saints in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>en is ſo exceeding glorious, that it is not poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ble for all the tongues of men or Angels to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>eſs it. But by the way, to give you ſome glimp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>s of this moſt excellent glorie, conſider a little <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>heſe following particulars.</p>
            <p>Firſt, in heaven we ſhall have the everlaſting <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>refence of God Himſelf: there we ſhall ſee God
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:179869:14"/>as He is, not by faith, but by ſight, clea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> and fullie. <hi>I ſhall ſee him</hi> (ſaith holy <hi>J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> with theſe eyes. Now we ſee as it were throug<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> glaſſe darkly, but there we ſhall ſee God fac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> face.</hi> We ſhall ſee Him as we are ſeen. Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> and there we ſhall be ever with the Lord, as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Apoſtle hath it, 1 <hi>Theſs.</hi> 4.17. We ſhall enjoy G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> in heaven freely and fully without let or in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption; Though the Saints may poſſiblie m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> with many and great impediments, and him rances in the way unto Heaven, yet in Hea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> there ſhall be nothing to hinder or inter<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> their joy. It is poſſible that a Child of G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> may have his skin pulled over his ears, as ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of the Apoſtles had in their way unto Hea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> yet being gotten into Heaven, nothing ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> leſt or trouble them at all. What an unſpe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able inconceiveable comfort will it be, Chri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, to have and enjoy the preſence of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> God who is all, and hath all, and will be e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſtinglie all in all to His people for ever: <hi>Wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> having not ſeen</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>we ſire to love: In whom believing, we rejoice w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> joy unſpeakable and full of glory.</hi> And if <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> fight of Gods preſence by faith be ſo glori<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> what then will be full fruition and enj<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God Himſelf be? O! unſpeakables <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> full of glorie.</p>
            <p>A ſecond thing which I would ſpeak to, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:179869:14"/>indeed I muſt but ſpeak to it, is the perfection of grace that ſhall be enjoyed in heaven? O Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, when ye come to heaven, then ye come to full age in heaven. <hi>The ſpirits of juſt men ſhal be made perfect, and the bodies of the Saints ſhal be made glorious even like the glorious body of Chriſt.</hi> There we ſhall do the will of God perfectlie. In heaven there is no ſin, nor tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptation to ſin, no not ſo much as a vain thought, or an idle word: And as there is no ſin, ſo there is no Satan. There ſhall be no more need of Sermons, nor Sacraments, nor Prayers: But the whole work of the Saints in heaven will be to ſing Praiſes and Hallelujahs to God for ever and ever.</p>
            <p>Thirdlie, in Heaven <hi>there is fulneſſe of joy, Rivers of pleaſures at Gods Right hand, and that for evermore, Pſalm</hi> 16.11. And thoſe Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers of pleaſures ſhall flow in, and from the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of God himſelf, as the Fountain of all thoſe joies, which have infiniteneſſe and eternitie in them, without the leaſt dram of ſorrow: <hi>For God ſhall then wipe away all tears from our eyes, and there ſhall be no more ſorrow, Rev.</hi> 21.4. The Rivers of the Saints joy in Heaven, as they are without bank, ſo they are without bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom: Our Maſters joy will then be ſo great, that we his Servants ſhall not be able to contain it: There is nothing in Heaven but what is
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:179869:15"/>matter of joy, our Fathers houſe, our Inhe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance our Kingdome, our Crown and Glory our ſight of Gods Face. That is an excellen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſpeech of <hi>David, Thou ſhalt make me</hi> (ſaith he <hi>full of joy with shy Countenance:</hi> Heaven is boundleſſe, yea, a bottomleſſe Ocean of joy an happineſſe, the ſociety of bleſſed Angels, at glorified Saints. In a word, the joies of Heave<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> far exceeds all the joies that can be thought o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> upon earth: Not onely the joy of Marriag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> and the joy of Harveſt, but alſo they joy of Fait<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> and the joy of Ordinances, which are all ſwa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed up by this great Ocean of joy: Nothin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> can diſturb or diminiſh the joies of the Saints <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Heaven.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, as there is fulneſſe of joy in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, ſo there is excellency of glory; Perfection of glory ſhall be the Saints Robes: <hi>In Heaven they ſhall ſhine as the Stars for ever and ever Dan.</hi> 12.5. In the one and twentieth of the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velations,</hi> St. <hi>John</hi> ſpeaking of the new Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem, exactly deſcribes the glory thereof: <hi>It is Citty, whoſe walls are Jaſper, and the ſtre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pure Gold, clear as Chriſtal, whoſe foundation are of precious Stones, and the gates thereof <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Pearles:</hi> And if this new Jeruſalem, the Church of God here below be ſo glorious, how exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing glorious then is that heavenly Jeruſalem which is above? Heaven, as one ſaith, is the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:179869:15"/>Palace of the King of Glory, the Preſence cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the great God, whoſe Preſence it is that makes Heaven to be Heaven: There indeed would be no Heaven, if God Himſelf were not there. In Heaven God makes His Glory viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, both to Saints and Angels: Thence it is called a Crown of Glory, an eternal weight of Glory: Glory ſhall then and there cover the Saints all over, from top to toe, both within and without, their Souls ſhall there be made glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious in knowledge, wiſdom, and underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and their bodies ſhall be made like the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Body of Chriſt; The bodies of the Saints in Heaven ſhall be free from all neceſſities of nature, as food, and raiment, ſleep, and the like. In Heaven there ſhall be no need of theſe things.</p>
            <p>Secondly, in Heaven the bodies of the Saints ſhall be freed from all natural infirmities, and deformities, ſickneſſe: diſeaſes, pains, or ſuch like bodily infirmities: There ſhall be no Crip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, no Blinde nor Diſeaſed ones in Heaven: Heaven is an healthful Countrie, there is no ſickneſſe, nor death, no poverty nor diſgrace in Heaven: Our bodies ſhall be cloathed in Heaven with life and immortality by Chriſt: Chriſt will there change our vile bodies, and make them like His glorious Body, <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.21. Did <hi>Moſes</hi> face ſhine when he beheld but the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:179869:16"/>glorie of Gods out-ſide: Did <hi>Stephens</hi> face ſhin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> with Angelicall ſplendor or brightneſſe, ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> gloriouſlie then ſhall the glorious bodies of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Saints ſhine when they ſhall ſtand before the Lord of Glorie? The Saints then ſhall be, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> the Pſalmiſt expreſſes it, <hi>All glorious within their cloathing ſhall be all wrought gold.</hi> Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> glorie which Gods People ſhall ſee and enjoy i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Heaven, will infinitely oblidge them to ſpen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> eternity there. Take a little view, a foretaſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> as it were of the Saints glorie in Heaven. Firſt it is great, an exceeding, exceſſive, and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall weight of glory, as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> expreſſes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.17. The glory of Heaven is the glor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of glories, joy unſpeakable and full of glories unu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>terable and unconceiveable: Therefore it called, <hi>Glory to be revealed, Rom.</hi> 8.18. S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> a little the greatneſſe of this heavenly glories theſe two things: Firſt, the veſſels that ta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> it; Secondly, the reſemblance that ſets it forth. The veſſels that take in this glorie are the ſou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and bodies of Saints, whom the Apoſtle call <hi>Veſſels of mercy prepared unto glory:</hi> Firſt for the ſoul here in this life: The whole wor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> is not able to fill or ſatisfie one ſouls. The ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> is capable of more then the whole world is ab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> to give it: But the glory of Heaven, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> will fill all the ſouls of all the Saints brim-full. W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> read of ſome Saints that they live their full
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:179869:16"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aies: They had as it were their ballyful of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>his life, but in the life to come all the Saints <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hall be filled full of Glory. Secondly, for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he bodies of the Saints, though they are Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels of leſſe quantity then the ſoul, yet the world <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> not able to fill or ſatisfie the body to the full: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>s to inſtance in the Eye and the Ear, thoſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ttle Members of our Bodie. We uſe to ſay of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ome, that their Eye is bigger then their Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>le: The little Eye at one glance can take into <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> more then half the world; And what abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of noiſe and found will the Ear receive at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>nce. <hi>The Eye is not ſatisfied</hi> (as the Wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man ſaith, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 1.8.) <hi>with ſeeing, nor the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ar with hearing.</hi> Thoſe little members of our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ody are either clogged or tyred out, before <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hey can be filled or ſatisfied with thoſe things: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ut not only the ſouls, but even the bodies of The Saints in Heaven ſhall be filled top-full of Glory, from the crown of their heads to the ſole of their feet. In Heaven the everlaſting doors of our ſouls ſhall alwayes ſtand wide open to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the glory of Chriſt in the ſtreams thereof: and then ſhall Chriſt the King of Glory come in, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd dwell with them for ever.</p>
            <p>Secondly, the greatneſſe of the Saints Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in Heaven may further appear by the reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blances that ſets it forth: Firſt, the glory of Kings upon their Coronation day: That greatly
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:179869:17"/>ſets forth and illuſtrates the greatneſſe of Saints Glory in Heaven: For in Heaven Saints ſhall all be crowned Kings, and ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> reign as Kings for ever in Glory: They ſhall <hi>herit the Kingdom</hi> (as our Saviour ſaith, <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> 25.34.) <hi>prepared for them from the foundation the World.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The Glory of the Stars that alſo reſem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> the Glory of the Saints in Heaven. <hi>One Star fereth from another in Glory,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.41. the very bodies of the Saints in heaven ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſhine all the Glory of all the Stars; Yea, the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Glory of the Sun it ſelf, which out ſhiner all Glory of the Stars. See what our Saviour ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.23. <hi>Then ſhall the Righteous ſhine fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> as the Sun, in the Kingdom of their Father.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. The Glory of the glorious Angels, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> another reſemblance of the Saints in Glo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> the Glory of the Angels, that far exeeds all Glory of all the Stars, yea, and all the Kings Monarchs of the world: But the Saints in H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven <hi>ſhall be like unto the very Angels, M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> 22.30. Or as St. <hi>Luke</hi> hath it, <hi>Luk,</hi> 20. <hi>Equal to the Angles in Glory.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. The Glory of Chriſt Himſelf, who is L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of Glory, that reſembles and ſets forth the Gl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of the Saints: <hi>When Chriſt comes to be glori<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> in his Saints at the laſt day, then ſhall the Sai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> appear with Chriſt in Glory.</hi> Chriſt is the Glo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:179869:17"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f the Saints here, and Chriſt will be the Glory of the Saints hereafter: Chriſt will then put His Glory upon them, and they ſhall ſhine with the Glory thereof <hi>Then they ſhall be like Him,</hi> as St. <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ohn</hi> ſaith 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.2. <hi>For we ſhall ſee him as he is.</hi> Then the bodies of the Saints, which have lien <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>n the duſt, ſhall ariſe and put on beautifull gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ents, even the Robes of Glory. Chriſt will then <hi>change their vile bodies, and make them like to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>is glorious body:</hi> The Saints ſhall be made con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>mable to Chriſt in Glory. Is not then the Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the Saints in Heaven exceeding great? You <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e it is a King-like, a Star-like, a Saint-like, an <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ngel-like, yea, a Chriſt-like Glory.</p>
            <p>Secondly, the Glory of Heaven is ſolid, ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tantial, and weighty: the Apoſtle, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.17. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>lls it, <hi>an exceeding eternall weight of Glory.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>'s like to precious things, as Gold and Crowns, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e more weighty they are, the more worth is in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>em: Hence the Original word ſighifies both <hi>Weight and Glory.</hi> Whereas on the contrary, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>orldly glory, that's light and frothy, having no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>bſtance nor reality in them, they are only ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows that appear, and then vaniſh away: A faſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as the Apoſtle calls it, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.31. that paſſeth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>way: It is like a Picture that hath only ſhape and colour, but no life; meer fantaſie, a ſound and no more.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Heavenly Glory that is permanent
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:179869:18"/>and durable, it is laſting; Yea, an eve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing glory: It is perpetuall, it ſhall never nor decay: But worldly honour and glory, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> tranſitory, inconſtant, periſhing, and paſſing way like a feather in the air: it is only ſeen blown away with the wind, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.24. <hi>the glory of man is as the flower of the gra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> in the morning it flouriſhes, but in the eve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> it is cut down and withered.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, the Glory of Heaven is ſatisfy and contenting; They that enjoy it ſhall fire no more: But for worldly glory, they have moſt of it, ſtill deſire more: but the S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> in Heaven ſhall have as much of Glory as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> can hold, yes, more then their hearts can <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> or deſire. All the Saints in Heaven ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> We are rich, and are full, we have all, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> bound. 1. In Heaven there is plenty of wea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> peace, and ſafety, reſt, and reward: Plenty wealth without want. The Treaſures of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven cannot be corrupted: There is no moth ruſt, nor thieves to ſteal them away. Heaven Treaſures can never fail, they are like the dows Oyl, they increaſe upon the Saints: T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> are bags that wax not old, <hi>unſearchable rich Epheſ.</hi> 3 8. The Gold of Glory can never be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> or ſummed up. Secondly, in Heaven then plenty of peace without trouble, ſafety with danger, triumph without war: There all enem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ies
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:179869:18"/>ſhall ceaſe, our bodily enemies ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e be reconciled unto us: And the enemies <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ur ſouls ſhall be all caſt into the lake of fire brimſtone. In Heaven there is no bloody <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>n to kill a righteous <hi>Abel;</hi> No luxurious So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ites to vex a righteous <hi>Lot;</hi> No <hi>Iſhmael</hi> off; No <hi>Shimri</hi> to curſe; No <hi>Eſau</hi> to terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> No <hi>Rabſhekah</hi> to rail; No <hi>Herod</hi> to perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> the people of God; No <hi>Judas</hi> to betray a our. In Heaven there is peace, not for tearm <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ats, but for ever and ever. Thirdly, in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ven there is plenty of reſt without wearineſs; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e is no work to do but what is pure delight; only work of the Saints in Glory will be to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Praiſes and Hallelujahs to God for ever and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>. Heaven will be a place of eaſe and reſt to wearie: <hi>There remaineth a reſt for the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ple of God, Heb.</hi> 8.9. 'Tis poſſible they may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>yred (as it were) here with doing the work God, or wearied with ſuffering perſecutions the ſake of Chriſt, <hi>But there remaineth a reſt them hereafter.</hi> O what a ſweet expreſſion is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>! Art thou troubled and turmoil'd here, thou it have reſt hereafter. <hi>Bleſſed are the dead <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>th die in the Lord</hi> (ſaid the Spirit) <hi>they reſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>m their labours, and their works do follow <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>m, Rev.</hi> 14.13. Fourthly, in Heaven there is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>nty of reward: Do you here ſuffer for <hi>righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs ſake great is your reward in heaven,</hi> ſaith
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:179869:19"/>our Saviour, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.10. Do you ſuffer for Chriſt here, you ſhall reign with Chriſt hereafter glory. <hi>The light afflictions of a Saint here, we work for him an exceeding and eternall weig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> of glory hereafter.</hi> Upon this account our bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Saviour calls on us to rejoyce in our ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.12. <hi>Rejoice</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>and be exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing glade, for great is your reward in heaven</hi> What we ſuffer for God we ſuffer for the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God, and upon that ſcore the Saints a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ſaid to be counted worthy of the kingom of Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.5. <hi>The ſufferings of this life are n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> worthy to be compared with the glory that ſhall be in the life to come.</hi> Do you labour hard he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> for God and his cauſe; do you ſpend, and a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> you ſpent in his ſervice? perhaps you may be bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> poorly requited by men: O but conſider, heaven is a large recompenſe of everlaſting reward. It ſaid of <hi>Moſes, Heb.</hi> 11. <hi>That he choſe rather ſuffer afflictions with the people of God, then enjoy the pleaſures</hi> (the ſeeming pleaſures) <hi>of ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> for a ſeaſon.</hi> For indeed they are but ſeeming pleaſures which continue but for a ſeaſon: <hi>An<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> counted the reproach of Chriſt greater riches them<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> all the honours of Egypt.</hi> For, ſaith the Apoſtle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>He had reſpect to the recompenſe of reward Moſes</hi> could ſee glory to come through all the ſufferings of this life. Heaven is our great Lor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and Maſters joy, where all his faithfull ſervant
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:179869:19"/>ſhall be received and rewarded to all eternity. Fifthly, In Heaven there is good company, bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſociety; God and Chriſt, and the holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit: Millions of millions of bleſſed Saints and glorious Angels. Then ſhall the Saints be ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered to their Father, yea, to their fathers and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>iends who are gone to Heaven before them. And is it not a happineſs think you to be among our friends? do you not think that time well <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ent here, which you ſpend in the enjoyment <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd embracements of your friends ſociety, whoſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ve and favour is altogether inconſtant and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>angeable? you may be taken from them, or they from you in a moment; O but your friends <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Heaven they are immortall, and their love is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>changeable; they and you ſhall then and there <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ve for ever, and enjoy one another, and rejoice <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ne with another for ever: but your deareſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>iends on earth muſt die, they muſt leave you, <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>t your joy in Heaven ſhall no man take from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>u.</hi> In Heaven there is God your Father, and Chriſt your Head, and Huſband, and Saviour, there, even in his humane nature wherein he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ffered death on the Croſſe for you: and your <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>omforter, God the holy Spirit is there, yea, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d all your friends. How mightily do children <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ng to go home to their fathers houſe, or a wife <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> her huſband: ſo earneſtly ſhould our ſouls <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſire to go to heaven, our fathers houſe, to Chriſt
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:179869:20"/>our head and huſband, where there is good pany only, and that to all eternity.</p>
            <p>And then laſtly, the Glory of Heaven is ſtant and permanent: In Heaven all is ſafe ſure, all things continue there fixed and imm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able. Heaven is an Inheritance ſettled upon Saints for ever, and ſealed unto them by broad Seal of Chriſts Blood.</p>
            <p>I have ſhewed you in part what thoſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of glory are, which the Saints ſhall e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> hereafter: I come now, and I muſt be brief <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a little touch on it already, to ſhow what thoſe loſſes and croſſes are which B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers may meet withall here below: and firſt the loſſes which you may meet withall in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> world. What are they? poor trifles, a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> pebble-ſtones as it were; a little earthly t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> ſure it may be, ſuch as is not conſiderable: S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> little what thoſe worldly enjoyments are wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> poſſibly thou mayeſt loſe for Chriſts ſake: F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> thou loſeſt nothing for Chriſt here, but wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> vanity and emptineſs; <hi>broken Ciſtrens that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> hold no water.</hi> For as one ſaith well. <hi>A w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of honours or pleaſures cannot ſatisfie one <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> with any ſolid comfort.</hi> Thou mayeſt as ſoon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> thy Cheſt with Grace, as thy heart with Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> There is not that in the Creature which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> look for: Experience tells us, a man may at o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> have a houſe full of Gold, and yet a heart ful<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:179869:20"/>ſorrow: They that enjoy the moſt of the world cannot ſay they have enough, therefore the loſſe of it is not conſiderable, not to be comparers with the gain of Heaven. Seconly, there is nothing thou loſeſt for Heaven, but what is the portion of the wicked: Wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dly comforts are wicked mens portions: Yea, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>s all the por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that ever they ſhall have either here or hereafter, <hi>Son, remember</hi> (ſaith <hi>Abraham</hi> to <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ves</hi> being in hell) <hi>that thou in thy life-time re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eiveſt thy good things.</hi> They that have their Heaven in this world ſhall have nothing in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in the world to come. Thirdly, thou canſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oſe nothing for Chriſt that can be profitable to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hee: All the outward good things of this life cannot ſanctifie, nor purchaſe one dram of ſaving Grace for thee: They may prove ſhare to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hee, or be occaſions of ſin to you, or draw you from Chriſt, as they did the Young-man in the Goſpel, but they will never drive you to Chriſt: and commonly they that have moſt of Gold have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eaſt of Grace, or rather no Grace at all. And as they cannot ſanctifie you ſo they cannot ſave you: They can neither ſhe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>er you from the judgements of God here, of from the ſtroke of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eath; Neither can they preſerve you from hell hereafter. Rich <hi>Dives</hi> went to hell, when poor <hi>Lozarus</hi> was carried unto Heaven; Wordly things cannot purchaſe Heaven, if the whole
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:179869:21"/>world would lend you their ſhoulders, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> could not lift you up to Heaven. Fourth there is nothing here below that is certain, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> things under the Sun are mutable, ſublu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> enjoyments, more changeable then the Mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> inconſtant even as the Winde, certain on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> in uncertainties: And as they are uncerta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> ſo they are corruptible and periſhing. Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> calls them meat that periſheth, <hi>Joh.</hi> 6.27. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> things which either moths or ruſt may conſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> or thieves may ſteal away from you, or they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> be deſtroyed by fire: which if you do poſſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> while you live, yet you muſt leave them beh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> you when you die: <hi>For as we brought noth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> into the World, ſo it is certain we ſhall carry <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> thing out of the world.</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.7.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, outward enjoyments are often v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> troubleſome, they bring many fears, many ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> much ſorrow and vexation: <hi>There is a car<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> get, and a care to keep riches,</hi> as the Wiſe n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> faith, <hi>All is vanity,</hi> ſo is it alſo <hi>vexation of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit.</hi> Worldly comforts they are like Roſes, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> have ſharp prickles as well as ſweet flowers. man may have much bitterneſſe in his leaſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> comforts here, therefore do not think much <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> part with all things here below for Chriſt; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> thou ſhalt be no loſer by the bargain; Thou ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>receive an hundred fold more in this life, and the world to come eternall life, Mark</hi> 10.30
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:179869:21"/>I come now in the next place, in a word, to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ew you what theſe Croſſes are which Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers do oftentimes undergo for the Kingdom of Heavens ſake: and they are very ſmall and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſiderable alſo, in reſpect of the glory that fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows. The Apoſtles endured as much tribulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons for the Kingdom of heavens ſake as poſſibly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ould be, yet what did they think of it? <hi>We <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ckon</hi> (ſaith St. <hi>Paul</hi>) <hi>that the afflictions of this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe are not worthy to be compared with the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that ſhall be.</hi> For firſt, they are but light: <hi>our light afflictions.</hi> And as they are light, ſo they are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>or ſhort; they are but for a moment: <hi>Our light affliction</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>which is but for a moment, worketh for us a far more exceeding and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ternall weight of glory.</hi> Hence it is that the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ints of old were ſo joyfull in all their tribulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: hence <hi>they rejoiced that they were counted worthy to ſuffer for the name of Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall come now to ſhew you how it is that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oſe Manſions of glory in Heaven will make <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ood all our loſſes and croſſes upon earth: and his appears further for theſe reaſons. For firſt, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> you have heard already, the glory of the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>fied Saint in heaven is infinite, and durable: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd therefore muſt needs exceed and make good <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> their loſſes, which as you have alſo heard, are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>te and uncertain. We uſe to account more of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oſe things which are durable and laſting, than thoſe things which are of no certainty.</p>
            <pb n="42" facs="tcp:179869:22"/>
            <p> Secondly, The only, yea, all the treaſures the Saints are laid up in Heaven; and what ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> any care for loſing a few triffles ſo long as th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> treaſure is ſafe? If a man loſe a few triff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> yet if he have a ſafe treaſury to go to, he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſoon make good ſo ſmall a loſſe. Beloved, all t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> things you do enjoy here are but triffles; but t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> things which you ſhall enjoy hereafter in h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, are no leſſe then a treaſure: a rich tr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſury, the ſtore-houſe of God himſelf, into <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> which he hath been treaſuring up for his Sai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> from the foundation of the world. I might much larger herein: but I will conclude all i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> word or two of Application.</p>
            <p>Is it ſo then that thoſe manſions of Glory p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> pared by Chriſt for Believers in Heaven, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> abundantly recompenſe and make good all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Loſſes and Croſſes which Believers meet with in the World? The I beſeech you <hi>ſet your fections upon things above, and not on things low.</hi> You ſee we live in ſlippery times, we ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> not ſay that any thing is certain here: O th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> labour to be ſure of ſomething hereafter. If th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> canſt not keep thy earthly inheritance, then bout to get an inheritance in heaven.</p>
            <p>Secondly, for I muſt be brief, If there be ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> glorious manſions in heaven: then labour to p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> pare your ſouls for heaven. But how ſhall we this, may ſome ſay? I anſwer, Theſe five way
<list>
                  <item>1. Wouldſt thou prepare thy ſelf for heav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="43" facs="tcp:179869:22"/>be fruitfull then in well doing, alwayes abound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the works of the Lord: be ſure to get that work done which God ſent you into the world to do; growing in grace is going to heaven: and grace here will make you fit and meet for glory hereafter.</item>
                  <item>2. Would you prepare for heaven? labour to purge your ſelves then from all ſin, by being un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potted in the world; for as Heaven is a place of happineſs, ſo it is a place of holineſs, into which nothing that is unclean can enter: it is only <hi>the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ure in heart that ſhall ſee God,</hi> Mat. 5.8.</item>
                  <item>3. Would you prepare for heaven? then get <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>our ſelves into a poſture of readineſſe to leave he world and go to Heaven every day, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ou may up and be gone when ever death calls <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>or you: ſo that when death comes, you may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ave nothing to do but to die. Death will not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ait when he cometh: if ye are not fit to die, ye <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>re not fit for heaven: death will not carry that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oul to heaven that is not ready when he comes. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>f you are not ready to die when ever death <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>omes, let me tell you, ye are not fit to live in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>other world. You know not at what hour Chriſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ay come or ſend his meſſenger Death for you: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>erefore be alwayes ready for heaven, becauſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eaven is alwayes ready for you. When the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>idegroom came, they that had Oil in their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mps, grace in their hearts, they went in to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>riage: but for thoſe that wanted oil, the door
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:179869:23"/>was ſhut againſt them, and they were ſhut from the marriage-feaſt. They that have la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> without oil, profeſſion without grace, ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver enter into Heaven.</item>
                  <item>4. Would you prepare for Heaven? then your title to Heaven cleared and confirme<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> you: what man is there, that having purch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> a great Eſtate, that will be ſo fooliſh as n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> get a ſure title to what he hath purchaſed? <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>we are ſtrangers and pilgrims, as all our fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> were;</hi> but heaven that's our home, our coun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> our Fathers Houſe, our Inheritance: O ſhould we then labour to make that ſure to ſouls! and having made that ſure, labour in the next place, to keep up your Evide<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> Firſt, keep your Evidences for Heaven and fair, for Satan will endeavour to blot t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> Secondly, keep them ſafe: the Devil wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> them from you if he can; and if ye loſe Evidences, what have you to ſhew for Hea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> If your writings be loſt, how will you get Inheritance? Then, whatſoever you do, ge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance of heaven; for firſt, aſſurance of he will take off your hearts from the world: rance of thoſe things above will make you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ing to part with all things here below, co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> you in all your tribulations, and bear up hearts under all diſcouragements, as it did <hi>vids, Jobs</hi> and <hi>Pauls.</hi> Evidence for Heaven lie warm at your hearts when naturall hea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="45" facs="tcp:179869:23"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>yes; when you lie upon your death beds, they <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>ill be a ſweet taſte to your Souls: when you <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eel no taſte or comfort in meat or drink, aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>ance of Heaven will comfort you: when all <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>ings fail you, aſſurance of Heaven will pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>are you for all changes, it will fit you for your <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>eat change. Aſſurance of life eternall will <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>onquer the Grave for you, and unſting Death <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>o you: it will make you ſing, yea, to triumph <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>n the way to heaven, over death and the grave. They that have Heaven aſſured to them, have more joy and gladneſs put into their ſouls, than <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>ll the world beſides. Aſſurance of ſalvation will <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>ngage you to truſt God for all things, and evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>ence God to your ſouls, it will make you to love <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>nd delight in him, fearfull to offend, carefull to <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>leaſe him. Thirdly, Aſſurance makes men <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>uſpicious of themſelves: they that are aſſur'd <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>hat they ſhall ſtand, will be ſure to take heed <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>hat they do not fall: they that ſhall be ſaved, <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>ill labour to work it out with fear. Fourthly, <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>ſſurance makes the ſoul humble; the higher the <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>oul is in aſſurance, the lower it will be in humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>ity. But how ſhall we know that our aſſurance <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>or heaven is right? Take theſe following Rules.
<list>
                        <item>1. Right aſſurance will make you more holy: every man that hath this hope purifies himſelf as God is pure. Right aſſurance for Heaven will <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>ngage your ſouls to be holy in all manner of converſation: <hi>Having therefore theſe promiſes.
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:179869:24"/>dearly beloved, cleanſe your ſelves from all thineſſe both of the fleſh and ſpirit,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.</item>
                        <item>2. Right aſſurance will make the ſoul to pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere to the end; <hi>receiving the end of your fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap> the ſalvation of your ſouls.</hi> But how ſhall get this aſſurance? 1. By having a godly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> row for ſin wrought in thy ſoul. Chriſt gives <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> to none but to the weary. 2. Examine your he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap> and lives by comparing them with the Word God. 3. Aſſurance is obtained by a holy, co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, and carefull uſe of the Ordinances of Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> in joining both the end and the means togeth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap> it will make you as carefull to uſe the means, confident to expect the end of your faith, <hi>the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                                 <desc>••</desc>
                              </gap>
                              <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of your ſouls.</hi> It doth not feed men w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> vain hopes, that they ſhall eſcape hell thou they live in ſin, and go on in the broad way t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap> leads to deſtruction. They that would come heaven muſt be carefull to uſe the means,<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> they muſt walk in that ſtrait and narrow w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> unto holineſſe and righteouſneſſe, which on leads unto life and ſalvation.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>And laſtly, is it ſo then that <hi>Godlines is great g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> yea, it is the beſt gain? Hath God made thee g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>The lines are fallen to thee in a pleaſant place, t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> haſt a goodly heritage,</hi> Pſal. 16.6. It is enough, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> haſt all: though it may be thou haſt but little the world yet thou haſt a propriety in God: G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> is thine, thy portion is Chriſt, he is thy Jeſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> thy all; Labour then to be conformable to Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:179869:24"/>godlineſs is Gods likeneſs. Hath God given you <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ace? God hath done more for you than if he <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>nd given you a thouſand worlds. Are others <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ch, and art thou poor? have others plenty of <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>old and ſilver, and haſt thou little or none ar all? <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>onſider, hath not God given thee that which is finitely better than all the Gold and Riches of <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>he World: Faith, that is more precious than Gold that periſhes: Wiſdom, that is better than <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>bies? yea all things that can be thought of are <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ot comparable to grace. If grace be thy portion, <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>lory will be thy portion: and thou haſt more <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>uſe of content, than if thou hadſt all the world <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>or thy portion without grace. What though o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>hers be richer than thee, yet thou art better than thers. <hi>The righteous is more excellent then his neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>r.</hi> Are others had in honour and art thou de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>piſed? let me tell thee, if thou haſt the favour of God, thou haſt more honour then all the world <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>n give. Are thy troubles greater nor others? con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, God ſeeth them good for thee; thou canſt or tell how to be without them: <hi>It is good for me</hi> ſaith <hi>David</hi>) <hi>that I have been afflicted,</hi> They that <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ave endured the moſt of afflictions here, will be <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>nd to be the happieſt people in all the world <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>reafter, for through them we enter into glory. <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>hrough many tribulations we muſt enter into the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>m of heaven.</hi> Unto which Kingdom the Lord, his infinite mercy, bring us all. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
